The Little Prince by Antoine de Saint exupery Audiobook edition 20 2020 by David De de Angelis All rights reserved
Narrated by Stephanie Richardson
To Leon Wirth
I ask the indulgence of the children who may read this book for dedicating it to a grownup
I have a serious reason
He is the best friend I have in the world
I have another reason this grown-up understands everything
even books about children
I have a third reason he lives in France
where he is hungry and cold
He needs cheering up
If all these reasons are not enough
I will dedicate the book to the child from whom this grown-up grew
All grown-ups were once children
although few of them remember it
and so I correct my dedication to Leon Worth when he was a little boy
One
once when I was six years old
I saw a magnificent picture in a book called True Stories from Nature about the primeval forest
It was a picture of a boa constrictor in the act of swallowing an animal
Here is a copy of the drawing in the book
It said boa constrictor swallow their prey whole without chewing it
After that
they are not able to move and they sleep through the six months that they need for digestion
I pondered deeply then over the adventures of the jungle
and after some work with a colored pencil
I succeeded in making my first drawing
my drawing number one
it looked something like this
I showed my masterpiece to the grownups and asked them whether the drawing frightened them
but they answered frighten
Why should anyone be frightened by a hat
My drawing was not a picture of a hat
it was a picture of a Boa constructor digesting an elephant
but since the grown ups were not able to understand it
I made another drawing
I drew the inside of a boa constrictor so that the grownups could see it clearly
They always need to have things explained
My drawing number two looked like this
The grownups response this time was to advise me to lay aside my drawings of boa constrictors
whether from the inside or the outside
and devote myself instead to geography
historyarithmetic
and grammar
That is why
at the age of six
I gave up what might have been a magnificent career as a painter
I had been disheartened by the failure of my drawing number one and my drawing number two grown ups never understand anything by themselves and it is tiresome for children to be always and forever explaining things to them
So then I chose another profession and learned to pilot airplanes
I have flown a little over all parts of the world
and it is true that geography has been very useful to me
At a glance
I can distinguish China from Arizona
If one gets lost in the night
Such knowledge is valuable
In the course of this life
I have had a great many encounters with a great many people who have been concerned with matters of consequence
I have lived a great deal among grown-ups
I have seen them intimately close at hand
and that hasn't much improved my opinion of them
Whenever I met one of them who seemed to me at all clear sighted
I tried the experiment of showing him my drawing number one
which I have always kept
I would try to find out
So if this was a person of true understanding
but whoever it was
he or she would always say that is a hat
Then I would never talk to that person about boa constructors or primeval forests or stars
I would bring myself down to his level
I would talk to him about bridge and golf and politics and neckties
and the grown up would be greatly pleased to have met such a sensible man
Two
so I lived my life alone without anyone that I could really talk to until I had an accident with my plane in the desert of Sahara six years ago
Something was broken in my engine
and as I had with me
neither a mechanic nor any passengers
I set myself to attempt the difficult repairs all alone
It was a question of life or death for me
I had scarcely enough drinking water to last a week the first night
Then I went to sleep on the sand
1000 miles from any human habitation
I was more isolated than a shipwrecked sailor on a raft in the middle of the ocean
thus you can imagine my amazement at sunrise when I was awakened by an odd little voice
It said
if you please draw me a sheep
what draw me a sheep
I jumped to my feet
completely thunderstruck
I blinked my eyes hard
I looked carefully all around me
and I saw a most extraordinary small person who stood there examining me with great seriousness
Here you may see the best portrait that later I was able to make of him
but my drawing is certainly very much less charming than its model
Thathowever
is not my fault
The grown ups discouraged me in my painter's career when I was six years old
and I never learned to draw anything except boas from the outside and boas from the inside
Now I stared at this sudden apparition with my eyes fairly starting out of my head in astonishment
Remember
I had crashed in the desert
1000 miles from any inhabited region
and yet my little man seemed neither to be straying uncertainly among the sands
nor to be fainting from fatigue or hunger or thirst or fear
Nothing about him gave any suggestion of a child lost in the middle of the desert
1000 miles from any human habitation
When at last I was able to speak
I said to him
but what are you doing here
And in answer he repeated very slowly
as if he were speaking of a matter of great consequence
If you please draw me a sheep
when a mystery is too overpowering
one dare not disobey
Absurd as it might seem to me
1000 miles from any human habitation
and in danger of death
I took out of my pocket a sheet of paper and my fountain pen
But then I remembered how my studies had been concentrated on geography
historyarithmetic
and grammar
and I told the little chap a little crossly
toothat I did not know how to draw
He answered me
that doesn't matter
draw me a sheep
But I had never drawn a sheep
so I drew for him one of the two pictures I had drawn so often
It was that of the boa constrictor from the outside
and I was astounded to hear the little fellow greeted with no
nono
noI do not want an elephant inside a boa constrictor
A boa constrictor is a very dangerous creature and an elephant is very cumbersome
Where I live
everything is very small
what I need is a sheep
draw me a sheep
So then I made a drawing
he looked at it carefully
then he said no
this sheep is already very sickly
make me another
So I made another drawing
My friend smiled gently and indulgently
You see yourself
he said that this is not a shape
this is a ram
it has horns
So then I did my drawing over once more
but it was rejected too
just like the others
this one is too old
I want a sheep that will live a long time by this time
my patience was exhausted because I was in a hurry to start taking my engine apart
so I tossed off this drawing and I threw out an explanation with it
This is only his box
the sheep you asked for is inside
I was very surprised to see a light break over the face of my young judge
that is exactly the way I wanted it
Do you think that this sheep will have to have a great deal of grass
why
Because where I live everything is very small
there will surely be enough grass for him
I said it is a very small sheep that I have given you he bent his head over the drawing
not so small that look he has gone to sleep
and that is how I made the acquaintance of the little prince
Three
it took me a long time to learn where he came from
The little prince who asked me so many questions never seemed to hear the ones I asked him
It was from words dropped by chance that little by little everything was revealed to me The first time he saw my airplane
For instance
I shall not draw my ai​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌rplane
That would be much too complicated for me
He asked me
what is that object
That is not an object
it flies
it is an airplane
it is my airplane
and I was proud to have him learn that I could fly
He cried out then what
you dropped down from the sky
YesI answered modestly
ohthat is funny
And the little prince broke into a lovely peal of laughter
which irritated me very much
I like my misfortunes to be taken seriously
Thenhe added
so you too come from the sky
which is your planet
At that moment I caught a gleam of light in the impenetrable mystery of his presence
and I demanded abruptly
do you come from another planet
But he did not reply
He tossed his head gently
without taking his eyes from my plane
It is true that on that you can't have come from very far away
and he sank into a reverie which lasted a long time
Thentaking my sheep out of his pocket
he buried himself in the contemplation of his treasure
You can imagine how my curiosity was aroused by this half confidence about the other planets
I made a great effort
thereforeto find out more on this subject
My little man
where do you come from
What is this where I live
of which you speak
Where do you want to take your sheep
After a reflective silence
he answered the thing that is so good about the box you have given me is that at night he can use it as his house
That is so
and if you are good
I will give you a string too
so that you can tie him during the day and a post to tie him to
But the little prince seemed shocked by this offer
Tie him
What a queer idea
But if you don't tie him
I said
he will wander off somewhere and get lost
My friend broke into another peal of laughter
but where do you think he would go
Anywhere straight ahead of him
Then the little prince said earnestly
that doesn't matter where I live
everything is so small
and with perhaps a hint of sadness he added straight ahead of him
nobody can go very far
FourI had thus learned a second fact of great importance
This was that the planet the little prince came from was scarcely any larger than a house
But that did not really surprise me much
I knew very well that in addition to the great planets such as the Earth
Jupiter Mars
Venusto which we have given names
there are also hundreds of others
some of which are so small that one has a hard time seeing them through the telescope
When an astronomer discovers one of these
he does not give it a name
but only a number
He might call it
for example
asteroid 325
I have serious reason to believe that the planet from which the little prince came is the asteroid known as B6 1 2
This asteroid has only once been seen through the telescope
That was by a Turkish astronomer in 19 oh 9
On making his discovery
the astronomer had presented it to the International Astronomical Congress in a great demonstration
but he was in Turkish costume
and so nobody would believe what he said
Grown ups are like that
Fortunatelyhowever
for the reputation of asteroid B 601 2
a Turkish vector made a law that his subjects
under pain of death
should change to European costume
So in 1920
the astronomer gave his demonstration all over again
dressed with impressive style and elegance
and this time everybody accepted his report
If I have told you these details about the asteroid and made a note of its number for you
it is on account of the grown ups and their ways
When you tell them that you have made a new friend
they never ask you any questions about essential matters
They never say to you what does his voice sound like
what games does he love best
Does he collect butterflies
Instead
They demand
how old is he
how many brothers has he
how much does he weigh
how much money does his father make
Only from these figures do they think they have learned anything about him
If you were to say to the grown ups
I saw a beautiful house made of rosy brick with geraniums in the windows and doves on the roof
they would not be able to get any idea of that house at all
You would have to say to them
I saw a house that cost $20000
Then they would exclaim
ohwhat a pretty house that is
Just so you might say to them
the proof that the little prince existed is that he was charming
that he left
and that he was looking for a sheep
If anybody wants a sheep
that is a proof that he exists
And what good would it do to tell them that they would shrug their shoulders and treat you like a child
But if you said to them the planet he came from is asteroid B 602
then they would be convinced and leave you in peace from their questions
They are like that
One must not hold it against them
Children should always show great forbearance toward grown up people
But certainly for us who understand life figures are a matter of indifference
I should have liked to begin this story in the fashion of the fairy tales
I should have liked to say once upon a time there was a little prince who lived on a planet that was scarcely any bigger than himself
and who had need of a sheep to those who understand life that would have given a much greater air of truth to my story
for I do not want anyone to read my book carelessly
I have suffered too much grief in setting down these memories
Six years have already passed since my friend went away from me with his sheep
If I try to describe him here it is to make sure that I shall not forget him to forget a friend is sad
not everyone has had a friend
and if I forget him
I may become like the grown ups who are no longer interested in anything but figures
It is for that purpose
againthat I have bought a box of paints and some pencils
It is hard to take up drawing again at my age when I have never made any pictures except those of the boa constrictor from the outside and the boa constrictor from the inside since I was 6
I shall certainly try to make my portraits as true to life as possible
but I am not at all sure of success
One drawing goes along all right
and another has no resemblance to its subject
I make some errors too in the little princess height in one place
he is too tall and in another too short
and I feel some doubts about the color of his costume
so I fumble along as best I can
Now good
now bad
and I hope
generally fair to middling in certain more important details
I shall make mistakes also
but that is something that will not be my fault
My friend never explained anything to me
He thought perhaps that I was like himself
but I
alasdo not know how to see sheep through the walls of boxes
Perhaps I am a little like the grown ups I have had to grow old
Five
as each day passed
I would learn in our talk something about the little prince's planet
his departure from it
his journey
The information would come very slowly
as it might chance to fall from his thoughts
It was in this way that I heard on the third day about the catastrophe of the baobabs
This time
once more I had the sheep to think for it
for the little prince asked me abruptly
as if seized by a grave doubt
It is true
isn't it
that sheep eat little bushes
Yesthat is true
I am glad I did not understand why it was so important that sheep should eat little bushes
but the little prince added
then it follows that they also eat baobabs
I pointed out to the little prince that baobabs were not little bushy
but on the contrary
trees as big as castles
and that even if he took a whole herd of elephants away with him
the herd would not eat up one single baobab
The idea of the herd of elephants made the little prince laugh
We would have to put them one on top of the other
he said
but he made a wise comment before they grow so big
The bow Babs start out by being little
That is strictly correct
I said
but why do you want the sheep to eat the little baobabs
He answered me at once
Ohcome
comecome
comeas if he were speaking of something that was self evident
and I was obliged to make a great mental effort to solve this problem without any assistance
Indeed
as I learned
there were on the planet where the little prince lived
as on all planets
good plants and bad plants
In consequence
there were good seeds from good plants and bad seeds from bad plants
But seeds are invisible
They sleep deep in the heart of the earth's darkness until someone among them is seized with the desire to awaken
Then this little seed will stretch itself and begin
timidly at first
to push a charming little sprig inoffensively upward toward the sun
if it is only a sprout of radish or the sprig of a rose bush
1 would let it grow wherever it might wish
But when it is a bad plant
one must destroy it as soon as possible
the very first instant that one recognizes it
Now there were some terrible seeds on the planet that was the home of the little prince
and these were the seeds of the baobab
the soil of that planet was infested with them
A baobab is something you will never
never be able to get rid of If you attend to it too late
it spreads over the entire planet
it bores clear through it with its roots
and if the planet is too small and the bow babs are too many
they split it in pieces
it is a question of discipline
the little prince said to me later on
when you finish your own toilet in the morning then it is time to attend to the toilet of your planet
just so with the greatest care you must see to it that you pull up regularly all the bow Babs at the very first moment when they can be distinguished from the rose bushes
which they resemble so closely in their earliest youth
It is very tedious work
the little prince added
but very easy and one day he said to me you ought to make a beautiful drawing
so that the children where you live can see exactly how all this is that would be very useful to them if they were to travel someday
sometimes he added there is no harm in putting off a piece of work until another day
but when it is a matter of baobabs
that always means a catastrophe
I knew a planet that was inhabited by a lazy man he neglected three little bushes
so as the little prince described it to me I have made a drying of that planet I do not much like to take the tone of a moralist
but the danger of the baobabs is so little understood
and such considerable risk would be run by anyone who might get lost on an asteroid that for once I am breaking through my reserve children I say plainly watch out for the baobabs my friends like myself have been skirting this danger for a long time without ever knowing it
and so it is for them that I have worked so hard over this drawing the lesson which I pass on by this means is worth all the trouble it has cost me
perhaps you will ask me why are there no other drawings in this book as magnificent and impressive as this drawing of the baobabs
the reply is simple I have tried
but with the others I have not been successful when I made the drawing of the baobabs I was carried beyond myself by the inspiring force of urgent necessity
Six
ohlittle prince
Bit by bit
I came to understand the secrets of your sad little life
For a long time you had found your only entertainment in the quiet pleasure of looking at the sunset
I learned that new detail on the morning of the fourth day when you said to me
I am very fond of sunsets
Come
let us go look at a sunset now
But we must wait
I said
wait for what
For the sunset
we must wait until it is time
At first you seemed to be very much surprised
and then you laughed to yourself
you said to me I am always thinking that I am at home
just so everybody knows that when it is noon in the United States
the sun is setting over France
If you could fly to France in one minute
you could go straight into the sunset right from noon
UnfortunatelyFrance is too far away for that
but on your tiny planet
my little prince
all you need to do is move your chair a few steps
you can see the day end and the twilight falling whenever you like
One day you said to me
I saw the sunset 44 times and a little later you added
you know
one loves the sunset when one is so sad
Were you so sad
Then I asked on the day of the 44 sunsets
but the little prince made no reply
Seven on the fifth day
Againas always
it was thanks to the sheep
The secret of the little prince's life was revealed to me abruptly
without anything to lead up to it
and as if the question had been born of long and science meditation on his problem
he demanded a sheep
If it eats little bushes
does it eat flowers too
A sheep
I answered
eats anything it finds in its reach
Even flowers that have thorns
Yeseven flowers that have thorns
Then the thorns
what use are they
I did not know
At that moment I was very busy trying to unscrew a bolt that had got stuck in my engine
I was very much worried
for it was becoming clear to me that the breakdown of my plane was extremely serious and I had so little drinking water left that I had to fear for the worst
The thorns
What use are they
The little Prince never let go of a question once he had asked it
as for me
I was upset over that bolt and I answered with the first thing that came into my head
The thorns are of no use at all
Flowers have thorns just for spite
Ohthere was a moment of complete silence
then the little prince flashed back at me with a kind of resentfulness
I don't believe you
flowers are weak creatures
they are naivety
they reassure themselves as best they can
they believe that their thorns are terrible weapons
I did not answer at that instant
I was saying to myself
if this bolt still won't turn
I am going to knock it out with the hammer again
The little prince disturbed my thoughts and you actually believe that the flowers
Oh no
I cried
Nono
nono
noI don't believe anything
I answered you with the first thing that came into my head
Don't you see
I am very busy with of consequence
He stared at me
thunderstruckmatters of consequence
He looked at me there with my hammer in my hand
my fingers black with engine grace
bending down over an object which seemed to him extremely ugly
You talk just like the grownups that made me a little ashamed
But he went on relentlessly
You mix everything up together
you confuse everything
He was really very angry
He tossed his golden curls in the breeze
I know a planet where there is a certain red faced gentleman
he has never smelled a flower
he has never looked at a star
he has never loved anyone
he has never done anything in his life but add up figures
And all day he says over and over
just like you
I am busy with matters of consequence and that makes him swell up with pride
But he is not a man
he is a mushroom
A what
a mushroom
the little prince was now white with rage
the flowers have been growing thorns for millions of years
For millions of years the sheep have been eating them just the same
and it is not a matter of consequence to try to understand why the flowers go to so much trouble to grow thorns which are never of any use to them
is the warfare between the sheep and the flowers not important
Is this not of more consequence than a fat red faced gentleman's sums
And if I know I myself 1 flower which is unique in the world
which grows nowhere but on my planet
but which one little sheep can destroy in a single bite some morning without even noticing what he is doing
Ohyou think that is not important
His face turned from white to red as he continued
If someone loves a flower of which just one single blossom grows in all the millions and millions of stars
it is enough to make him happy just to look at the stars
He can say to himself somewhere
my flower is there
But if the sheep eats the flower in one moment
all his stars will be darkened
And you think that is not important
He could not say anything more
His words were choked by sobbing
The night had fallen
I had let my tools drop from my hands
Of what moment now was my hammer
my bolt
or thirst or death on one star
1 planet
my planet
the earth
there was a little prince to be comforted
I took him in my arms and rocked him
I said to him
the flower that you love is not in danger
I will draw you a muzzle for your sheep
I will draw you a railing to put around your flower
I will
I did not know what to say to him
I felt awkward and blundering
I did not know how I could reach him
where I could overtake him
and go on hand in hand with him once more
It is such a secret place
the land of tears
Eight
I soon learned to know this flower better on the little princess planet
The flowers had always been very simple
They had only one ring of petals
they took up no room at all
they were a trouble to nobody
One morning they would appear in the grass
and by night they would have faded peacefully away
But one day
from a seed blown from no one knew where
a new flower had come up
and the little prince had watched very closely over the small sprout
which was not like any other small sprouts on his planet
It might
you see
have been a new kind of baobab
The shrub soon stopped growing and began to get ready to produce a flower
The little prince
who was present at the first appearance of a huge bud
felt at once that some sort of miraculous apparition must emerge from it
But the flower was not satisfied to complete the preparations for her beauty
In the shelter of her green chamber
she chose her colors with the greatest care
She dressed herself ​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌slowly
she adjusted her petals 1 by one
She did not wish to go out into the world all rumpled like the field poppies
It was only in the full radiance of her beauty that she wished to appear
Oh yes
she was a coquettish creature
and her mysterious adornment lasted for days and days
Then one morning
exactly at sunrise
she suddenly showed herself
and after working with all this painstaking precision
she yawned and said
I am scarcely awake
I beg that you will excuse me
My petals are still all disarranged
but the li​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌ttle prince could not restrain his admiration
Ohhow beautiful you are
am I not
The flower responded sweetly
and I was born at the same moment as the sun
The little prince could guess easily enough that she was not any too modest
but how moving and exciting she was
I think it is time for breakfast
she added
An instant later
if you would have the kindness to think of my needs
and the little prince
completely abashed
went to look for a sprinkling can of fresh water
so he tended the flower
so too she began very quickly to torment him with her vanity
which was
if the truth be known
a little difficult to deal with
One day
for instance
when she was speaking of her four thorns
she said to the little prince
let the tigers come with their claws
There are no tigers on my planet
the little prince objected
and anyway tigers do not eat weeds
I am not a weed
the flower replied sweetly
Please excuse me
I am not at all afraid of tigers
she went on
but I have a horror of giraffes
I suppose you wouldn't have a screen for me
a horror of giraffes
that is bad luck for a plant
remarked the little prince
and added to himself
this flower is a very complex creature
At night I want you to put me under a glass globe
It is very cold where you live
in the place I came from
but she interrupted herself at that point she had come in the form of a seed
she could not have known anything of any other worlds
embarrassed over having let herself be caught on the verge of such a naive untruth
she coughed two or three times in order to put the little prince in the wrong the screen
I was just going to look for it when you spoke to me
then she forced her cough a little more so that he should suffer from remorse just the same
so the little prince in spite of all the goodwill that was inseparable from his love
had soon come to doubt her
He had taken seriously words which were without importance
and it made him very unhappy
I ought not to have listened to her
He confided to me one day
one never ought to listen to the flowers
one should simply look at them and breathe their fragrance
mine perfumed all my planet
but I did not know how to take pleasure in all her grace
This tale of claws
which disturbed me so much
should only have filled my heart with tenderness and pity
and he continued his confidences
The fact is that I did not know how to understand anything I ought to have judged by deeds and not by words
She cast her fragrance and her radiance over me
I ought never to have run away from her
I ought to have guessed all the affection that lay behind her
poor little stratagems
Flowers are so inconsistent
but I was too young to know how to love her
Nine
I believe that for his escape
he took advantage of the migration of a flock of wild birds
On the morning of his departure
he put his planet in perfect order
He carefully cleaned out his active volcanoes
He possessed two active volcanoes
and they were very convenient for heating his breakfast in the morning
He also had one volcano that was extinct
but as he said
one never knows
So he cleaned out the extinct volcano
Twoif they are well cleaned out
volcanoes burn slowly and steadily without any eruptions
Volcanic eruptions are like fires in a chimney on our earth
We are obviously much too small to clean out our volcanoes
that is why they bring no end of trouble upon us
The little prince also pulled up with a certain sense of dejection
the last little shoots of the baobabs
He believed that he would never want to return
but on this last morning all these familiar tasks seemed very precious to him
and when he watered the flower for the last time and prepared to place her under the shelter of her glass globe
he realized that he was very close to tears
Good bye
he said to the flower
but she made no answer
Goodbyehe said again
The flower coughed
but it was not because she had a cold
I have been silly
she said to him at last I ask your forgiveness try to be happy he was surprised by this absence of reproaches
He stood there all bewildered
the glass globe held
arrested in mid air
He did not understand this quiet sweetness
Of course I love you
the flower said to him
it is my fault that you have not known it all the while
that is of no importance
but you have been just as foolish as I try to be happy
let the glass globe be
I don't want it any more
but the wind
my cold
is not so bad as all that the cool night air will do me good
I am a flower
but the animals well
I must endure the presence of two or three caterpillars if I wish to become acquainted with the butterflies
it seems that they are very beautiful
and if not the butterflies and the caterpillars who will call upon me
you will be far away
As for the large animals
I am not at all afraid of any of them
I have my claws
and naively she showed her four thorns
then she added
don't linger like this
you have decided to go away
now go for she did not want him to see her crying
She was such a proud flower
he found himself in the neighborhood of the asteroids
325 3 2 6 3 2 7
32 8 3 2 9
and 3 3 0
He began
thereforeby fisting them in order to add to his knowledge
The first of them was inhabited by a king clad in royal purple and ermine
He was seated upon a throne which was at the same time both simple and majestic
Here is a subject
exclaimed the king
when he saw the little prince coming
and the little prince asked himself
how could he recognize me when he had never seen me before
He did not know how the world is simplified for kings to them
all men are subjects
Approach so that I may see you better
said the king
who felt consumingly proud of being at last a king over somebody
The little prince looked everywhere to find a place to sit down
but the entire planet was crammed and obstructed by the king's magnificent ermine robe
so he remained standing upright
and since he was tired he yawned
It is contrary to etiquette to yawn in the presence of a king
The monarch said to him
I forbid you to do so
I can't help it
I can't stop myself
replied the little prince
Thoroughly embarrassed
I have come on a long journey
and I have had no sleep
Then the king said I order you to yawn
It is years since I have seen anyone yawning
Yawns to me are objects of curiosity
Come now
yawn again
It is an order that frightens me
I cannot any more
murmured the little prince
now completely abashed
Humreplied the king
then I order you sometimes to yawn
and sometimes to
he sputtered a little
and seemed vexed
for what the king fundamentally insisted upon was that his authority should be respected
He tolerated no disobedience
he was an absolute monarch
but because he was a very good man
he made his orders reasonable
If I ordered a general
he would say by way of example
if I ordered a general to change himself into a sea bud
and if the general did not obey me
that would not be the fault of the general
It would be my fault
May I sit down
Came now a timid inquiry from the little Prince
I order you to do so
the king answered him
and majestically gathered in a fold of his ermine mantle
but the little prince was wondering the planet was tiny over what could this king really rule
Sire
he said to him
I beg that you will excuse my asking you a question
I order you to ask me a question
the king hastened to assure him
sireover
what do you rule for everything
said the king with magnificent simplicity over everything the king made a gesture which took in his planet the other planets
and all the stars over all that
asked the little prince
over all that the king answered
for his rule was not only absolute
it was also universal
and the stars obey you
certainly they do
the king said they obey instantly
I do not permit insubordination
such power was a thing
for the little prince to marvel at
if he had been master of such complete authority he would have been able to watch the sunset not 44 times in one day
but 72 or even 100
or even 200 times without ever having to move his chair
and because he felt a bit sad as he remembered his little planet which he had forsaken
he plucked up his courage to ask the king a favor
I should like to see a sunset
do me that kindness order the sun to set if I ordered a general to fly from one flower to another
like a butterfly
or to write a tragic drama ought to change himself into a sea bird
and if the general did not carry out the order that he had received
which one of us would be in the wrong
the king demanded the general or myself
you said the little prince firmly
exactly one must require from each one the duty which each one can perform the king went on
accepted authority rests first of all on reason
if you ordered your people to go and throw themselves into the sea
they would rise up in revolution
I have the right to require obedience
because my orders are reasonable
then my sunset
the little prince reminded him
for he never forgot a question
once he had asked it
you shall have your sunset
I shall command it
but according to my science of government
I shall wait until conditions are favorable
when will that be inquired the little prince hum
humhum
replied the king
and before saying anything else he consulted a bulky almanac
hum that will be about about that will be this evening about 20 minutes to 8
and you will see how well I am obeyed
The little prince yawned
He was regretting his lost sunset
and then
toohe was already beginning to be a little bored
I have nothing more to do here
he said to the king
so I shall set out on my way again
Do not go
said the king
who was very proud of having a subject
Do not go
I will make you a minister
Minister of what
Minister of of justice
But there is nobody here to judge
We do not know that the king said to him
I have not yet made a complete tour of my kingdom
I am very old
there is no room here for a carriage
it tires me to walk
Oh
but I have looked already
said the little prince
turning around to give one more glance to the other side of the planet
On that side
as on this
there was nobody at all
Then you shall judge yourself
the king answered
That is the most difficult thing of all
It is much more difficult to judge oneself than to judge authors
If you succeed in judging yourself rightly
then you are indeed a man of true wisdom
Yes
said the little prince
but I can judge myself anywhere
I do not need to live on this planet
Humhum
humsaid the king
I have good reason to believe that somewhere on my planet there is an old rat
I hear him at night
You can judge this old rat from time to time
You will condemn him to death
Thus his life will depend on your justice
but you will pardon him on each occasion
for he must be treated thriftily
He is the only one we have
I replied
The little prince do not like to condemn anyone to death
and now I think I will go on my way
Nosaid the king
but the little prince
having now completed his preparations for departure
had no wish to grieve the old monarch
If your Majesty wishes to be promptly obeyed
he said
he should be able to give me a reasonable order
He should be able
for example
to order me to be gone by the end of one minute
It seems to me that conditions are favorable
as the king made no answer
The little prince hesitated a moment
thenwith a sigh
he took his leave
I make you my ambassador
the king called out hastily
He had a magnificent air of authority
The grown ups are very strange
the little prince said to himself as he continued on his journey
the second planet
was inhabited by a conceited man
I am about to receive a visit from an admirer
he exclaimed from afar when he first saw the little prince coming
for to conceited men all other men are admirers
Good morning
said the little prince
that is a queer hat you are wearing
It is a hut for salutes
the conceited man replied
It is to raise in salute when people acclaim me
Unfortunatelynobody at all ever passes this way
Yessaid the little prince
who did not understand what the conceited man was talking about
clap your hands
one against the other
the conceited man now directed him
the little prince clapped his hands
the conceited man raised his hat in a modest salute
This is more entertaining than the visit to the king
the little prince said to himself
and he began again to clap his hands
one against the other
The conceited man again raised his hat in salute after five minutes of this exercise
the little prince grouped tired of the game's monotony
and what should one do to make the hat come down
he asked
But the conceited man did not hear him
Conceited people never hear anything but praise
Do you really admire me very much
he demanded of the little prince
What does that mean
Admire to admire means that you regard me as the handsomest
the best dressed the richest
and the most intelligent man on this planet
But you are the only man on your planet
Do me this kindness
admire me just the same
I admire you
said the little prince
shrugging his shoulder slightly
but what is there in that to interest you so much
And the little prince went away
The grown ups are certainly very odd
he said to himself as he continued on his journey
12 the next planet was inhabited by a tippler
This was a very short visit
but it plunged the little prince into deep dejection
What are you doing there
He said to the tippler
whom he found settled down in silence before a collection of empty bottles and also a collection of full bottles
I'm drinking
replied the Tippler with a lugubrious air
Why are you drinking
demanded the little prince
So that I may forget
replied the tippler
Forget what
inquired the little prince
who already was sorry for him
Forget that I am ashamed
the tippler confessed
hanging his head
ashamed of what insisted the little prince who wanted to help him
ashamed of drinking the tippler
brought his speech to an end and shut himself up in an impregnable silence
and the little prince went away puzzled
The grown ups are certainly very
ve​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌ry odd
he said to himself as he continued on his journey
the fourth planet belonged to a businessman
This man was so much occupied that he did not even raise his head at the little prince's arrival
Good morning
the little prince said to him
Your cigarette has gone out
Three and 2 make 5
5 and 7 make 12 and 3 make 15
Good morning
15 and 7 make 22
22 and 6 make 28
I haven't time to light it again
26 and 5 make 31 few
Then that makes 501622731 500 million
What asked the little prince
ehare you still there
501 million
I can't stop
I have so much to do
I'm concerned with matters of consequence
I don't amuse myself with baldar dash 2 and 5 make 7 501 million What repeated the little prince who never in his life had let go of a question once he had asked it
The business man raised his head during the 44 years that I have inhabited this planet
I have been disturbed only three times
The first time was 22 years ago when some giddy goose fell from goodness knows where
He made the most frightful noise that resounded all over the place
and I made four mistakes in my edition
The second time
11 years ago
I was disturbed by an attack of rheumatism
I don't get enough exercise
I have no time for loafing the third time
Wellthis is it
I was saying then 501 millions
millions of what
The business man suddenly realized that there was no hope of being left in peace until he answered this question
Millions of those little objects
he said
which one sometimes sees in the sky flies
Ohno
little glittering objects
Peaceoh no
little golden objects
That's a lazy man title dreaming
As for me
I am concerned with matters of consequence
There is no time for idle dreaming in my life
You mean the stars
Yesthat's it
the stars
and what do you do with 500 millions of stars
501622731
I am concerned with matters of consequence
I am accurate
And what do you do with these stars
what do I do with them
Yesnothing
I owned them
You own the stars
yesbut I have already seen a king who kings do not own
they reign over is a very different matter and what good does it do you to own the stars
It does me the good of making me rich
and what good does it do you to be rich
It makes it possible for me to buy more stocks if any are discovered
This man
the little prince said to himself
reasons a little like my poor tippler
nevertheless he still had some more questions
How is it possible for one to own the stars
To whom do they belong
The business man retorted peevishly
I don't know to nobody
then they belong to me
because I was the first person to think of it
Is that all that is necessary
certainly when you find a diamond that belongs to nobody
it is yours
when you discover an island that belongs to nobody
made it yours
When you get an idea before anyone else
you take out a patent on it
it is yours
So with me
I own the stars because nobody else before me ever thought of owning them
Yes
that is true
said the little prince
and what do you do with them
I administer them
replied the businessman
I count them and recount them
It is difficult
but I am a man who is naturally interested in matters of consequence
The little prince was still not satisfied
If I owned a silk scarf
he said
I could put it around my neck and take it away with me
If I owned a flower
I could pluck that flower and take it away with me
But you cannot pluck the stars from heaven
Nobut I can put them in the bank
whatever does that mean
That means I write the number of my stars on a little paper
and then I put this paper in a drawer and lock it with a key
and that is all
That is enough
said the business
man
It is entertaining
thought the little prince
It is rather poetic
but it is of no great consequence
On matters of consequence
the Little Prince had ideas which were very different from those of the grown ups
I myself own a flower
He continued his conversation with the businessman
which I water every day
I own three volcanoes
which I clean out every week
for I also clean out the one that is extinct
One never knows it is of some use to my volcanoes
and it is of some use to my flower that I owned them
But you are of no use to the stars
The businessman opened his mouth
but he found nothing to say in answer and the little prince went away
The grown ups are certainly altogether extraordinary
he said
simply talking to himself as he continued on his journey
the fifth planet was very strange
It was the smallest of all
There was just enough room on it for a street lamp and a lamp lighter
The little prince was not able to reach any explanation of the use of a street lamp and a lamp lighter somewhere in the heavens on a planet which had no people and not one house
But he said to himself
neverthelessit may well be that this man is absurd
but he is not so absurd as the king
the conceited man
the business man
and the tippler
For at least his work has some meaning
When he lights his street lamp
it is as if he brought one more star to life
or one flower
When he puts out his lamp
he sends the flower or the star to sleep
That is a beautiful occupation
and since it is beautiful
it is truly useful
When he arrived on the planet
he respectfully saluted the lamplighter
Good morning
why have you just put out your lamp
Those are the orders
replied the lamplighter Good morning
What are the orders
The orders are that I put out my lamp
good evening
and he lighted his lamp again
But why have you just lighted it again
Those are the orders
replied the lamplighter
I do not understand
said the little prince
There is nothing to understand
said the lamplighter
orders are orders
Good morning
and he put out his lamp
then he mopped his forehead with a handkerchief decorated with red squares
I follow a terrible profession
In the old days it was reasonable
I put the lamp out in the morning
and in the evening I lodged it again
I had the rest of the day for relaxation and the rest of the night for sleep
and the orders have been changed since that time
The orders have not been changed
said the lamplighter
That is the tragedy
From year to year the planet has turned more rapidly and the orders have not been changed
Then what asked the little prince
then the planet now makes a complete turn every minute
and I no longer have a single second for repose
once every minute I have to light my lamp and put it out
That is very funny
A day lasts only one minute
Here where you live
it is not funny at all
said the lamplighter
while we have been talking together a month has gone by a month
yesa month
40 minutes
30 days
good evening
and he lighted his lamp again
as the little prince watched him
he felt that he loved this lamp lighter
who was so faithful to his orders he remembered the sunsets which he himself had gone to seek in other days merely by pulling up his chair
and he wanted to help his friend
You know
he said
I can tell you a way you can rest whenever you want to
I always want to rest
said the lamplighter
for it is possible for a man to be faithful and lazy at the same time
The little prince went on with his explanation
Your planet is so small that three strides will take you all the way around it to be always in the sunshine
you need only walk along rather slowly when you want to rest
you will work
and the day will last as long as you like
That doesn't do me much good
said the lamp ladder
The one thing I love in life is to sleep
then you're unlucky
said the little prince
I am unlucky
said the lamplighter
good morning and he put out his lamp
that man
said the little prince to himself as he continued farther on his journey
That man would be scorned by all the others
by the king
by the conceited man
by the tippler
by the business man
Neverthelesshe is the only one of them all who does not seem to me ridiculous
Perhaps that is because he is thinking of something else besides himself
He breathed a sigh of regret and said to himself again
that man is the only one of them all whom I could have made my friend
but his planet is indeed too small
There was no room on it for two people
What the little prince did not dare confess was that he was sorry most of all to leave this planet because it was blessed every day with 1440 sunsets
15 The sixth planet was 10 times larger than the last one
It was inhabited by an old gentleman who wrote voluminous books
Ohlook
here is an explorer
he exclaimed to himself when he saw the little prince coming
The little prince sat down on the table and panted a little
He had already travelled so much and so far
Where do you come from
The old gentleman said to him
What is that big book
said the little prince
what are you doing
I am a geographer
said the old gentleman
What is a geographer
asked the little prince
A geographer is a scholar who knows the location of all the seas
riverstowns
mountains and deserts
That is very interesting
said the l​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌ittle prince
Here at last is a man who has a real profession
and he cast a look around him at the planet of the geographer
It was the most magnificent and stately planet that he had ever seen
Your planet is very beautiful
he said
Has it any oceans
I couldn't tell you
said the geographer
The little prince was disappointed
Has it any mountains
I couldn't tell you
said the geographer
and towns and rivers and deserts
I couldn't tell you that either
but you are a geographer
exactlythe geographer said
but I am not an explorer
I haven't a single explorer on my planet
It is not the geographer who goes out to count the towns
the rivers
the mountains
the siege
the oceans
and the deserts
The geographer is much too important to go loafing about
He does not leave his desk
but he receives the explorers in his study
He asks them questions
and he notes down what they recall of their travels
and if the recollections of any one among them seem interesting to him
The geographer orders an inquiry into that explorer's moral character
Why is that
Because an explorer who told lies would bring disaster on the books of the geographer
so what an explorer who drank too much
why is that
asks the little prince
Because intoxicated men see double
then the geographer would note down two mountains in a place where there was only 1
I know someone said the little prince
who would make a bad explorer
That is possible
thenwhen the moral character of the explorer is shown to be good
an inquiry as ordered into his discovery
one goes to see it
Nothat would be too complicated
but one requires the explorer to furnish proofs
for example
if the discovery and question is that of a large mountain
one requires that large stones be brought back from it
The geographer was suddenly stirred to excitement
But you come from far away
you are an explorer
you shall describe your planet to me
and having opened his big register
the geographer sharpened his pencil
The recitals of explorers are put down first in pencil
one waits until the explorer has furnished proofs before putting them down in ink
Wellsaid the geographer expectantly
Oh
where I live
said the little prince
it is not very interesting
it is all so small
I have three volcanoes
two volcanoes are active and the other is extinct
but one never knows
one never knows
said the geographer
I have also a flower
we do not record flowers
said the geographer
Why is that the flower is the most beautiful thing on my planet
We do not record them
said the geographer
because they are etherol
What does that mean
Ephemeral geographies
said the geographer
are the books which of all books are most concerned with matters of consequence
They never become old fashioned
it is very rarely that a mountain changes its position
It is very rarely that an ocean identities itself of its waters
We write of eternal things
but extinct volcanoes may come to life again
The little prince interrupted
What does that mean
ephemeral
Whether volcanoes are extinct or alive
it comes to the same thing for us
said the geographer
the thing that matters to us is the mountain
it does not change
But what does that mean
Ephemeralrepeated
the little prince who never in his life had let go of a question once he had asked it
it means which is in danger of speedy disappearance
is my flower in danger of speedy disappearance
Certainly it is
my flower is ephemeral
the little prince said to himself
and she has only four thorns to defend herself against the world
and I have left her on my planet all alone
That was his first moment of regret
but he took courage once more
What place would you advise me to visit now
he asked
The planet Earth
replied the geographer
it has a good reputation
and the little prince went away thinking of his flower
16so then the seventh ​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌planet was the Earth
The Earth is not just an ordinary planet
One can count there 111 kings
not forgetting to be sure
the Negro kings
among them
7000 geographers
900000 businessmen
7500000 tipplers
311 million conceited men
that is to say
about 2 billion grown ups
To give you an idea of the size of the earth
I will tell you that before the invention of electricity it was necessary to maintain over the whole of the six continents a veritable army of 462511 lamplighters for the street lamps seen from a slight distance that would make a splendid spectacle
The movements of this army would be regulated like those of the ballet
In the opera
First would come the turn of the lamplighters of New Zealand and Australia
Having set their lamps light
these would go off to sleep
next the lamplighters of China
and Siberia would enter for their steps in the dance
and then they too would be waved back into the wings
After that​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌ would come the turn of the lamplighters of Russia and the Indies
then those of Africa and Europe
then those of South America
then those of North America
and never would they make a mistake in the order of their entry upon the stage
It would be magnificent
only the man who was in charge of the single lamp at the North Pole and his colleague who was responsible for the single lamp at the South Pole
Only these two would live free from toil and care
They would be busy twice a year
when one wishes to play the wit
he sometimes wanders a little from the truth
I have not been altogether honest in what I have told you about the lamplighters
and I realize that I run the risk of giving a false idea of our planet to those who do not know it
Men occupy a very small place upon the earth
If the 2 billion inhabitants who people its surface were all to stand upright and somewhat crowded together
as they do for some big public assembly
they could easily be put into one public square 20 miles long and 20 miles wide
All humanity could be piled up on a small Pacific islet
The grownups
to be sure
will not believe you when you tell them that
They imagine that they fill a great deal of space
They fancy themselves as important as the baobabs
You should advise them then
to make their own calculations
They adore figures
and that will please them
but do not waste your time on this extra task
It is unnecessary
You have
I know
confidence in me
When the little prince arrived on the earth
he was very much surprised not to see any people
He was beginning to be afraid he had come to the wrong planet when a coil of gold the color of the moonlight flashed across the sand
Good evening
said the little prince courteously
said the snake
what planet is this on which I have come down
asked the little prince
This is the earth
this is Africa
the snake answered
Then there are no people on the earth
this is the desert
there are ​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌no people in the desert
The earth is large
said the snake
The little prince sat down on a stone and raised his eyes toward the sky
I wonder
he said
whether the stars are set alight in heaven so that one day each one of us may find his own again
Look at my planet
It is right there above us
but how far away it is
it is beautiful
the snake said
What has brought you here
I have been having some trouble with a flower
said the little prince
Said the snake
and they were both science
Where are the men
The little prince at last took up the conversation again
It is a little lonely in the desert
It is also lonely among men
the snake said
The little prince gazed at him for a long time
You are a funny animal
he said at last
you are no thicker than a finger
but I am more powerful than the finger of a king
said the snake
The little prince smiled
You are not very powerful
you haven't even any feet
you cannot even travel
I can carry you farther than any ship could take you
said the snake
He twined himself around the little prince's ankle like a golden bracelet
Whomever I touch I send back to the earth from whence he came
The snake spoke again
but you are innocent and true
and you come from a star
The little prince made no reply
You move me to pity
You are so weak on this earth made of granite
the snake said
I can help you some day if you grow to homesick for your own planet
I can
ohI understand you very well
said the little prince
but why do you always speak in riddles
I solve them all
said the snake
and they were both science
the little Prince crossed the desert and met with only one flower
It was a flower with three petals
a flower of no account at all
Good morning
said the little prince
said the flower
Where are the men
the little prince asked politely
The flower had once seen a caravan passing
menshe echoed
I think there are 6 or seven of them in existence
I saw them several years ago
but no one knows where to find them
The wind blows them away
they have no roots
and that makes their life very difficult
Good bye
said the little prince
said the flower
19 after that
the little prince climbed a high mountain
The only mountains he had ever known were the three volcanoes
which came up to his knees
and he used the extinct volcano as a footstool from a mountain as high as this one
He said to himself
I shall be able to see the whole planet at one glance
and all the people
But he saw nothing save peaks of rock that were sharpened like needles
Good morning
he said courteously
good morning
answered the echo
Who are you
said the little prince
who are you
who are you answered the echo
Be my friends
I am all alone
he said
all alone
Answered the echo
What a queer planet
he thought
It is altogether dry
and altogether pointed and altogether harsh and forbidding
and the people have no imagination
They repeat whatever one says to them
On my planet I had a flower
she always was the first to speak
but it happened that after walking for a long time through sand and rocks and snow
the little prince at last came upon a road
and all roads lead to the abodes of men
Good morning
he said
He was standing before a garden
all abloom with roses
Good morning
said the roses
The little prince gazed at them
They all looked like his flower
Who are you
he demanded
thunderstruck
We are roses
the roses said
and he was overcome with sadness
His flower had told him that she was the only one of her kind in all the universe
and here were 5000 of them
all alike
in one single garden
She would be very much annoyed
he said to himself
if she should see that she would cough most dreadfully
and she would pretend that she was dying to avoid being laughed at
and I should be obliged to pretend that I was nursing her back to life
For if I did not do that to humble myself also
she would really allow herself to die
Then he went on with his reflections
I thought that I was rich with a flower that was unique in all the world
and all I had was a common rose
a common rose
and three volcanoes that come up to my knees
and one of them perhaps extinct forever
That doesn't make me a very great prince
And he lay down in the grass and cried
It was then that the fox appeared
Good morning
said the fox
The little prince responded politely
although when he turned around he saw nothing
I am right here
the voice said
under the apple tree
Who are you
asked the little prince
and added you are very pretty to look at
I am a fox
The fox said come and play with me
proposed the little prince
I am so unhappy I cannot play with you
The fox said I am not tamed
Please excuse me
said the little prince
but after some thought he added
what does that mean
tame
You do not live here
said the fox
what is it that you are looking for
I am looking for men
said the little prince
What does that mean
Tame men
said the fox
They have guns and they hunt
It is very disturbing
they also raise chickens
these are their only interests
Are you looking for chickens
Nosaid the little prince
I am looking for friends
what does that mean
Tame
It is an act too often neglected
said the fox
It means to establish ties
to establish ties
Just that
said the fox
To me
you are still nothing more than a little boy who is just like 100000 other little boys
and I have no need of you
and you on your part have no need of me
To you I am nothing more than a fox like 100000 other foxes
But if you tame me
then we shall need each other
To me you will be unique in all the world
To you
I shall be unique in all the world
I am beginning to understand
said the little prince
there is a flower
I think
that she has tamed me
It is possible
said the fox
On the earth
1 sees all sorts of things
Ohbut this is not on the earth
said the little prince
The fox seemed perplexed and very curious
On another planet
yesare there hunters on that planet
Nothat is interesting
are there chickens
Nonothing is perfect
sighed the fox
then he came back to his idea
My life is very monotonous
the fox said
I hunt chickens
men hunt me
all the chickens are just alike
and all the men are just alike
and in consequence I am a little bored
But if you tame me
it will be as if the sun came to shine on my life
I shall know the sound of a step that will be different from all the others
Other steps send me hurrying back underneath the ground
Yours will call me like music out of my burrow
And then
lookyou see the grain fields down yonder
I do not eat bread
wheat is of no use to me
the wheat fields have nothing to say to me
and that is sad
but you have hair that is the color of gold
Think how wonderful that will be when you have tamed me
The grain
which is also golden
will bring me back the thought of you
and I shall love to listen to the wind in the wheat
The fox gazed at the little prince for a long time
please pay me
he said I want to very much
the little prince replied
but I have not much time
I have friends to discover and a great many things to understand
One only understands the things that one tames
said the fox
Men have no more time to understand anything
they buy things already made at the shops
but there is no shop anywhere where one can buy friendship
and so men have no friends anymore
If you want a friend
tame me
What must I do to tame you
asked the little prince
You must be very patient
replied the fox
First you will sit down at a little distance from me like that in the grass
I shall look at you out of the corner of my eye
and you will say nothing
Words are the source of misunderstandings
But you will sit a lit​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌tle closer to me every day
The next day the little prince came back
It would have been better to come back at the same hour
said the fox
Iffor example
you come at 4 o'clock in the afternoon
then at 3 o'clock I shall begin to be happy
I shall feel happier and happier as the hour advances
At 4 o'clock I shall already be worrying and jumping about
I shall show you how happy I am
but if you come at just any time
I shall never know at what hour my heart is to be ready to greet you
One must observe the proper rights
What is a right asked the little prince
Those also are actions too often neglected
said the
They are what makes one different from other days
one hour from other hours
There is a right
For example
among my hunters
every Thursday they dance with the village girls
so Thursday is a wonderful day for me
I can take a walk as far as the vineyards
but if the hunters danced at just any time
every day would be like every other day
and I should never have any vacation at all
So the little prince tamed the fox
and when the hour of his departure drew near
said the fox
I shall cry
It is your own fault
said the little prince
I never wished you any sort of harm
but you wanted me to tame you
Yesthat is so
said the fox
But now you are going to cry
said the little prince
Yesthat is so
said the fox
Then it has done you no good at all
It has done me good
said the fox
because of the color of the wheat fields
and then he added
go and look again at the roses
You will understand now that yours is unique in all the world
Then come back to say goodbye to me and I will make you a present of a secret
The little prince went away to look again at the roses
You are not at all like my rose
he said
As yet you are nothing
no one has tamed you and you have tamed no one
You are like my fox
When I first knew him
he was only a fox
like 100000 other foxes
But I have made him my friend and now he is unique in all the world
And the roses were very much embarrassed
You are beautiful
but you are empty
he went on
One could not die for you to be sure
an ordinary passer by would think that my rose looked just like you
the rose that belongs to me
But in herself alone she is more important than all the hundreds of you other roses
because it is she that I have watered
because it is she that I have put under the glass globe
because it is she that I have sheltered behind the screen
because it is for her that I have killed the caterpillars
except the two or three that we saved to become butterflies
because it is she that I have listened to when she grumbled or boasted
or even sometimes when she said nothing
because she is my rose and he went back to meet the fox goodbye he said goodbye
said the fox
and now here is my secret
a very simple secret
It is only with the heart
that one can see rightly
what is essential is invisible to the eye
the little prince repeated so that he would be sure to remember
it is the time you have wasted for your rose
that makes your rose
so important
it is the time I have wasted for my rose
said the little prince
so that he would be sure to remember men have forgotten this truth
said the fox
but you must not forget it
you become responsible forever for what you have tamed you are responsible for your rose
I am responsible for my rose
the little prince repeated
so that he would be sure to remember
Good morning
said the little prince
said the railway switchman
What do you do here
the little prince asked
I sort out travellers in bundles of 1000
said the switched man
I send off the trains and carry them now to the right
now to the left
and a brilliantly lighted express train shook the switchman's cabin as it rushed by with a roar like thunder
They are in a great hurry
said the little prince
What are they looking for
Not even the locomotive engineer knows that
said the switchman
and a second brilliantly lighted express thundered by in the opposite direction
Are they coming back already demanded the little prince
These are not the same ones
said the switchman
It is an exchange
Were they not satisfied where they were
asked the little prince
No one is ever satisfied where he is
said the switchman
and they heard the roaring thunder of a third brilliantly lighted express
Are they pursuing
The first Travelers demanded the little prince
They are pursuing nothing at all
said the switchman
they are asleep in there
or if they are not asleep
they are yawning
Only the children are flattening their noses against the window panes
Only the children know what they are looking for
said the little prince
They waste their time over a rag doll
and it becomes very important to them
and if anybody takes it away from them
they cry
They are lucky
this witch man said
Good morning
said the little prince
said the merchant
This was a merchant who sold pills that had been invented to queries Thirst
You need only swallow one pill a week and you would feel no need of anything to drink
Why are you selling though
asked the little prince
Because they save a tremendous amount of time
said the merchant
computations have been made by experts with these pills
You say 53 minutes in every week
And what do I do with those 53 minutes
Anything you like
As for me
said the little prince to himself
if I had 53 minutes to spend as I liked
I should walk at my leisure toward a spring of fresh water
It was now the eighth day since I had had my accident in the desert
and I had listened to the story of the merchant as I was drinking the last drop of my water supply
I said to the little prince
these memories of yours are very charming
but I have not yet succeeded in repairing my plane
I have nothing more to drink
and I too should be very happy if I could walk at my leisure toward a spring of fresh water
My friend the fox
the little prince said to me
my dear little man
this is no longer a matter that has anything to do with the fox
why not because I am about to die of thirst
He did not follow my reasoning and he answered me
It is a good thing to have had a friend
even if one is about to die
Ifor instance
am very glad to have had a fox as a friend
he has no way of guessing the danger
I said to myself
he has never been either hungry or thirsty
A little sunshine is all he needs
but he looked at me steadily and replied to my thought
I am thirsty to let us look for a well
I made a gesture of weariness
it is absurd to look for a well at random in the immensity of the desert
but nevertheless we started walking when we had trudged along for several hours in silence
the darkness fell and the stars began to come out
Thirst had made me a little feverish
and I looked at them as if I were in a dream
The little prince's last words came reeling back into my memory
then You are thirsty too
I demanded
but he did not reply to my question
he merely said to me
water may also be good for the heart
I did not understand this answer
but I said nothing
I knew very well that it was impossible to cross examine him
he was tired
he sat down
I sat down beside him
and after a little silence he spoke again
The stars are beautiful because of a flower that cannot be seen
I replied yes
that is so
And without saying anything more
I looked across the ridges of sand that were stretched out before us in the moonlight
The desert is beautiful
the little prince added
and that was true
I have always loved the desert
One sits down on a desert sand dune
sees nothing
here's nothing
yet through the silence something throbs and gleams
what makes the desert beautiful
said the little prince
is that somewhere it hides a well
I was astonished by a sudden understanding of that mysterious radiation of the sands
When I was a little boy
I lived in an old house
and legend told us that a treasure was buried there to be sure no one had ever known how to find it
perhaps no one had ever even looked for it
but it cast an enchantment over that house
My home was hiding a secret in the depths of its heart
YesI said to the little prince
the house
the stars
the desert
what gives them their beauty is something that is invisible
I am glad
he said that you agree with my fox as the little prince dropped off to sleep
I took him in my arms and set out walking once more
I felt deeply moved and stirred
It seemed to me that I was carrying a very fragile treasure
It seemed to me even that there was nothing more fragile on all earth in the moonlight
I looked at his pale forehead
his closed eyes
his locks of hair that trembled in the wind
and I said to myself
what I see here is nothing but a shell
What is most important is invisible
As his lips opened slightly with the suspicion of a half smile
I said to myself again
what moves me so deeply about this little prince who is sleeping here is his loyalty to a flower
the image of a rose that shines through his whole being like the flame of a lamp even when he is asleep
And I felt him to be more fragile still
I felt the need of protecting him
as if he himself were a flame that might be extinguished by a little puff of wind and as I walked on so I found the well at daybreak
25 men said the little prince set out on their way in express trains
but they do not know what they are looking for
Then they rush about and get excited and turn round and round
And he added
it is not worth the trouble
The well that we had come to was not like the wells of the Sahara
The wells of the Sahara are mere holes dug in the sand
This one was like a well in a village
but there was no village here
and I thought I must be dreaming
It is strange
I said to the little prince
everything is ready for use
The pulley
the bucket
the rope
He laughed
touched the rope and set the pulley to working
And the pulley moaned like an old weather vane which the wind has long since forgotten
Do you hear
said the little prince
We have wakened the well
and it is singing
I did not want him to tire himself with the rope
leave it to me
I said
it is too heavy for you
I hoisted the bucket slowly to the edge of the well and set it there
Happytired as I was over my achievement
the song of the pulley was still in my ears and I could see the sunlight shimmer in the still trembling water
I am thirsty for this water
said the little prince
give me some of it to drink
and I understood what he had been looking for
I raised the bucket to his lips
he drank
his eyes closed
It was as sweet as some special festival treat
This water was indeed a different thing from ordinary nourishment
its sweetness was born of the walk under the stars
the song of the pulley
the effort of my arms
It was good for the heart
like a present When I was a little boy
the lights of the Christmas tree
the music of the midnight mass
the tenderness of smiling faces used to make up
so the radiance of the gifts I received
The men where you live
said the little prince raise 5000 roses in the same garden
and they do not find in it what they are looking for They do not find it
I replied
and yet what they are looking for could be found in one single rose or in a little water
Yesthat is true
I said
and the little prince added
but the eyes are blind
One must look with the heart
I had drunk the water
I breathed easily at sunrise
the sand is the color of honey
and that honey color was making me happy too
What brought me then
this sense of grief
You must keep your promise
said the little prince softly as he sat down beside me once more
What promise
you know
a muzzle for my sheep
I am responsible for this flower
I took my rough drafts of drawings out of my pocket
the little prince looked them over and laughed as he said your bow Babs
they look a little like cabbages
OhI had been so proud of my bow Babs
your fox
his ears look a little like horns and they are too long and he laughed again
You are not fair little prince
I said
I don't know how to draw anything except boa constructors from the outside and boa constrictors from the inside
Ohthat will be all right
he said
Children understand
So then I made a pencil sketch of a muzzle and as I gave it to him
my heart was torn
You have plans that I do not know about
I said
but he did not answer me
he said to me instead
you know my descent to the earth
tomorrow will be its anniversary
Thenafter a silence
he went on
I came down very near here and he flushed
and once again
without understanding why
I had a queer sense of sorrow
One question
howeveroccurred to me then
It was not by chance that on the morning when I first met you a week ago
you were strolling along like that
all alone
1000 miles from any inhabited region
You are on your way back to the place where you landed
The little prince flushed again
and I added with some hesitancy
Perhaps it was because of the anniversary
the little prince flushed once more
He had never answered questions
but when one flushes does that not mean yes
I said to him
I am a little frightened
but he interrupted me
Now you must work
You must return to your engine
I will be waiting for you here
come back tomorrow evening
but I was not reassured
I remembered the Fox 1 runs the risk of weeping a little if 1 let's himself be tamed
Beside the well there was the ruin of an old stone wall
When I came back for my work the next evening
I saw from some distance away my little prince sitting on top of a wall with his feet dangling
And I heard him say
then you don't remember
this is not the exact spot
Another voice must have answered him for
He replied to it
Yesyes
it is the right day
but this is not the place
I continued my walk toward the wall
At no time did I see or hear anyone
The little prince
howeverreplied once again
exactlyyou will see where my track begins in the sand
you have nothing to do but wait for me there
I shall be there tonight
I was only 20 m from the wall and I still saw nothing
After a silence
the little prince spoke again
You have good poison
you are sure that it will not make me suffer too long
I stopped in my tracks
my heart torn asunder
but still I did not understand
Now go away
said the little prince
I want to get down from the wall
I dropped my eyes then to the foot of the wall
and I leaped into the air
There before me
facing the little prince
was one of those yellow snakes that take just 30 seconds to bring your life to an end
Even as I was digging into my pocket to get out my revolver
I made a running step back
but at the noise I made
the snake let himself flow easily across the sand like the dying spray of a fountain
and in no apparent hurry
disappeared with a light metallic sound among the stones
I reached the wall just in time to catch my little man in my arms
His face was white as snow
What does this mean
I demanded
Why are you talking with snakes
I had loosened the golden muffler that he always wore
I had moistened his temples and had given him some water to drink
and now I did not dare ask him any more questions
He looked at me very gravely and put his arms around my neck
I felt his heart beating like the heart of a dying bird shot with someone's rifle
I am glad that you have found what was the matter with your engine
he said
Now you can go back home
How did you know about that
I was just coming to tell him that my work had been successful beyond anything that I had dared to hope
He made no answer to my question
but he added I too am going back home to then
Sadly
it is much farther
It is much more difficult
I realized clearly that something extraordinary was happening
I was holding him close in my arms as if he were a little child
and yet it seemed to me that he was rushing headlong toward an abyss from which I could do nothing to restrain him
His look was very serious
like some one lost far away
I have your sheep
and I have the sheep's box
and I have the muzzle
and he gave me a sad smile
I waited a long time
I could see that he was reviving little by little
dear little man
I said to him
you are afraid
He was afraid
there was no doubt about that
but he laughed lightly
I shall be much more afraid this evening
Once again I felt myself frozen by the sense of something irreparable
and I knew that I could not bear the thought of never hearing that laughter anymore
For me it was like a spring of fresh water in the desert
Little man
I said
I want to hear you laugh again
But he said to me tonight
it will be a year
My star then can be found right above the place where I came to the earth a year ago
Little man
I said
tell me that is only a bad dream
this affair of the snake and the meeting place and the star
But he did not answer my plea
He said to me instead
the thing that is important is the thing that is not seen
Yes
I know it is just as it is with the flower
If you love a flower that lives on a star
it is sweet to look at the sky at night
all the stars are abloom with flowers
YesI know
it is just as it is with the water becau​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌se of the pulley and the rope
What you gave me to drink was like music
you remember how good it was
YesI know
and at night you will look up at the stars where I live
​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌everything is so small that I cannot show you where my star is to be found
It is better like that
My star will just be one of the stars for you and so you will love to watch all the stars in the heavens
they will all be your friends and besides I'm going to make you a present
He laughed again
Little prince
dear little prince
I love to hear that laughter
that is my present
just that it will be as it was when we drank the water
What are you trying to say
All men have the stars
he answered
but they are not the same things for different people
For some who are travelers
the stars are guides
for others there are no more than little lights in the sky
for others who are scholars
they are problems
For my business man
they were wealth
but all these stars are science
You alone will have the stars as no one else has them
What are you trying to say in one of the stars
I shall be living in one of them
I shall be laughing
and so it will be as if all the stars were laughing
When you look at the sky at night
you only you will have stars that can laugh
And he laughed again
and when your sorrow is comforted
time soothed all sorrows
you will be content that you have known me
you will always be my friend
you will want to laugh with me
and you will sometimes open your window
so for that pleasure
and your friends will be properly astonished to see you laughing as you look up at the sky
Then you will say to them
yesthe stars always make me laugh
and they will think you are crazy
It will be a very shabby trick that I shall have played on you
and he laughed again
it will be as if in place of the stars
I had given you a great number of little bells that knew how to laugh
and he laughed again
Then he quickly became serious
Tonight
you know
do not come
I shall not leave you
I said
I shall look as if I were suffering
I shall look a little as if I were dying
It is like that
do not come to see that it is not worth the trouble
I shall not leave you
But he was worried
I tell you it is also because of the snake
he must not bite you snakes
they are malicious creatures
this one might bite you just for fun
I shall not leave you
but a thought came to reassure him
it is true that they have no more poison for a second bite that night I did not see him set out on his way
he got away from me without making a sound when I succeeded in catching up with him he was walking along with a quick and resolute step
he said to me merely you are there and he took me by the hand
but he was still worrying it was wrong of you to come
you will suffer
I shall look as if I were dead
and that will not be true
I said nothing
You understand it is too far
I cannot carry this body with me
It is too heavy
I said nothing
but it will be like an old abandoned shell
There is nothing sad about old shells
I said nothing
He was a little discouraged
but he made one more effort
You know it will be very nice
I too shall look at the stars
All the stars will be wells with a rusty pulley
All the stars will pour out fresh water for me to drink
I said nothing
that will be so amusing
You will have 500 million little bells and I shall have 500 million springs of fresh water
and he too said nothing more because he was crying
Here it is
let me go on by myself
And he sat down because he was afraid
Then he said again
you know
my flower
I am responsible for her and she is so weak
she is so naive
She has four thorns of no use at all to protect herself against all the world
I too sat down because I was not able to stand up any longer there
Now that is all
He still hesitated a little
then he got up
he took one step
I could not move
there was nothing but a flash of yellow close to his ankle
He remained motionless for an instant
he did not cry out
he fell as gently as a tree falls
there was not even any sound because of the sand
27 and now six years have already gone by
I have never yet told this story
The companions who met me on my return were well content to see me alive
I was sad
but I told them I am tired
Now my sorrow is comforted a little
that is to say
not entirely
but I know that he did go back to his planet because I did not find his body at daybreak
It was not such a heavy body
and at night I loved to listen to the stars
It is like 500 million little bells
but there is one extraordinary thing when I drew the muzzle for the little prince
I forgot to add the leather strap to it
He will never have been able to fasten it on his sheep
So now I keep wondering what is happening on his planet
Perhaps the sheep has eaten the flower at one time
I say to myself
surely not
the little prince shuts his flower under her glass globe every night and he watches over his sheep very carefully
then I am happy
and there is sweetness in the laughter of all the stars
But at another time I say to myself
at some moment or other one is absent minded
and that is enough
On some one evening he forgot the glass globe
or the sheep got out without making any noise in the night
and then the little bells are changed to tears
Here
thenis a great mystery for you
who also love the little prince
and for me
nothing in the universe can be the same if somewhere we do not know where a sheep that we never saw has yes or no Eaton arose
Look up at the sky
Ask yourselves
is it yes or no
Has the sheep eaten the flour
And you will see how everything changes
And no grownup will ever understand that this is a matter of so much importance
This is to me
the loveliest and saddest landscape in the world
It is the same as that on the preceding page
but I have drawn it again to impress it on your memory
It is here that the little Prince appeared on earth and disappeared
Look at it carefully so that you will be sure to recognize it in case you travel someday to the African desert
and if you should come upon this spot
please do not hurry on
Wait for a time exactly under the star
Thenif a little man appears who laughs
who has golden hair
and who refuses to answer questions
you will know who he is
If this should happen
please comfort me
send me word that he has come back
This has been the Little Prince by Antoine de Santa book edition 2020 by David de Angelus
All rights are reserved
Narrated by Stephanie Richardson
Production copyright 20 2020 by David d'angeli